<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">

<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">

<front>


<article-meta>


<title-group>
<article-title>ESS 330 Project Proposals</article-title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Zelenz</surname>
<given-names>Ava</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Ava Zelenz</string-name>

<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original
draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eastman</surname>
<given-names>Avery</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Avery Eastman</string-name>

<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="writing – original
draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">writing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>CSU</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1"></corresp>
</author-notes>









<history></history>






</article-meta>

</front>

<body>
<sec id="section-1-ava">
  <title>Section 1 Ava</title>
  <sec id="title-monarch-butterfly-decline-in-the-u.s.">
    <title>Title: Monarch Butterfly Decline in the U.S.</title>
    <p>Justification: The loss of biodiversity is something that we are
    seeing more and more of as climate change worsens. This topic is one
    that I have experience observing back home in New York. Throughout
    the past 20 or so years, there has been a heavy decrease in the
    amount of monarch sightings across the country, with an estimated
    81% decline in monarchs from 1999 to 2010
    (<xref alt="Pleasants &amp; Oberhauser, 2013" rid="ref-pleasants2013milkweed" ref-type="bibr">Pleasants
    &amp; Oberhauser, 2013</xref>). Monarch population decline is linked
    to the decline of milkweed population, as they feed primarily on
    this. Long-term plant surveys have been utilized to evaluate the
    correlation of milkweed and monarchs, which found a 68% loss of
    milkweed available to monarchs
    (<xref alt="Zaya, Pearse, &amp; Spyreas, 2017" rid="ref-zaya2017long" ref-type="bibr">Zaya,
    Pearse, &amp; Spyreas, 2017</xref>). This is a significant problem
    because monarchs are on track to become endangered and extinct, and
    if the statistics and data show this a main contributor for the
    decline of milkweed, we can change that and hopefully bring back the
    population of monarchs and avoid a loss of species and more
    biodiversity.</p>
    <p>Research objective/question/hypothesis: Decline in milkweed
    growth leads to the decline of monarch populations in the U.S.</p>
    <p>Proposed Methods: The variables I would like to measure are
    monarch population, milkweed growth within the U.S., and a time span
    of 20 years. I will perform a statistic test to determine their
    correlation based on the data that I find. I will also plot the
    results I get. I will look at the data.gov and on Nature Scientific
    Data, to find datasets that show the monarch and milkweed
    correlation. I will also look at DataCite for more data. This scope
    will be within the U.S. Before I start with my correlation tests, I
    will assess normality and skewness in the data, and make adjustments
    to clean the data if necessary.</p>
    <p>Expected Outcomes: I would expect to find that there is a
    statistically significant value that shows a positive correlation
    between milkweed and monarch population.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section-2">
  <title>Section 2</title>
  <sec id="title-how-colorado-is-impacted-by-nonnative-plants">
    <title>Title: How Colorado is Impacted By Nonnative Plants</title>
    <p>Justification: Colorado is home to very unique plants which serve
    the connected ecosystem. With birds, fish, insects, and other
    animals relying on these native plants, they can be threatened by
    nonnative species and their presence in Colorado. With the presence
    of these nonnative species, there are uncertain effects that can
    pose problems
    (<xref alt="Byrne, Lauenroth, &amp; McManus, 2010" rid="ref-byrne2010impacts" ref-type="bibr">Byrne,
    Lauenroth, &amp; McManus, 2010</xref>). The determination of if
    these nonnative species in Colorado are harmful or helpful needs to
    be looked into and researched more. There have been studies in Rocky
    Mountain National Park, that state there is a uneven distribution of
    native and nonnative plants within RMNP, and that this biological
    and geological difference is a contributing factor of the
    relationship between these two types of plant
    (<xref alt="Kumar, Stohlgren, &amp; Chong, 2006" rid="ref-kumar2006spatial" ref-type="bibr">Kumar,
    Stohlgren, &amp; Chong, 2006</xref>). To understand this
    relationship would prove to be helpful to the biodiversity of
    Colorado, as there are many fragile ecosystems within the state that
    will either be negatively or positively impacted by nonnative
    species.</p>
    <p>Research objective/question/hypothesis: How does the relationship
    between nonnative and native plant species change throughout
    Colorado?</p>
    <p>Proposed methods: The variables I would include would be the
    nonnative species within Colorado, the native species, and a time
    span of around 25-30 years, as plants and their influence on the
    environments around them take a long time to show effects. I will
    perform a statistic test to determine their correlation based on the
    data that I find as well as plotting the results I get. I’ve found a
    datasets on data.gov about nonnative plants, and areas of critical
    environmental concern, both in Colorado, as the scope will be just
    Colorado. Again, I will be looking at the datasets to take into
    consideration the skewness of the data, as make changes
    accordingly.</p>
    <p>Expected Outcomes: I expect theses outcomes to be not straight
    forward, like my previous proposal. Due to previous knowledge, the
    influence of nonnative plants on biodiversity is a very complex
    relationship, so I think in parts of the data there will be points
    of proof that there is a negative and positive correlation between
    the two and their interactions.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section-3-avery">
  <title>Section 3 Avery</title>
  <sec id="proposal-1-shifts-in-bird-migration-patterns-due-to-changing-climate">
    <title>Proposal 1: Shifts in Bird Migration Patterns Due to Changing
    Climate</title>
    <p>Justification: As human-caused climate change continues to
    accelerate at concerning levels, it is essential to track the
    responding changes in ecosystems in order to conserve and sustain
    them. All organisms will be affected by these changes and will
    either have to adapt or face the risk of extinction. In response to
    climate change, one change we can expect to see across many species
    is, change in migration and distribution patterns. Migratory birds
    contribute significantly to various ecosystems, and according to
    (<xref alt="Koleček, Adamı́k, &amp; Reif, 2020" rid="ref-kolevcek2020shifts" ref-type="bibr">Koleček,
    Adamı́k, &amp; Reif, 2020</xref>), increasing temperatures leads to
    shifts in species abundance. Shift in abundance are extremely
    important to monitor from a sustainability standpoint. Ecosystems
    offer many services that we rely on, hence part of the importance in
    conserving and sustaining them. In addition,
    (<xref alt="Tomotani et al., 2018" rid="ref-tomotani2018climate" ref-type="bibr">Tomotani
    et al., 2018</xref>) reports that climate change may ultimate lead
    to negative changes in bird species fitness. Migratory birds also
    play a role in maintaining plant and vegetation growth through seed
    dispersal. Thus, shifts in their migratory patterns could negatively
    effect plant growth.</p>
    <p>Research objective/question/hypothesis: Through this study I aim
    to discover how bird migratory behavior is affected by climate
    change. My hypothesis is: changes in temperature and weather
    patterns are drivers of shifts in bird migration. I will use a
    regression model to assess the relationship between climate
    (independent variable) and bird migration (dependent variable).</p>
    <p>Proposed Methods: I plan to use a dataset that shows climate
    (including variables such as temperature, precipitation, rainfall,
    etc) throughout many year, which I then plan to filter to the U.S.
    and a 10 year timeframe. I also plan to use data on bird migration
    patterns (this may be several dataset), that show variables such as
    species, geographic info, distance traveled, migration times (start,
    end, variability). Additionally, if needed I will narrow my spatial
    scope by choosing 6-12 different states to look at. Before I do any
    statistical testing on my data I will be testing for a normal
    distribution. If it is not normally distributed I will have to use
    different statistic tests.</p>
    <p>Expected Outcomes: I expect to see a relationship between change
    in climate and change in migration patterns, thus I expect to reject
    the null hypothesis. This is an important outcome to get because it
    will be reflective of the current threat of climate change to
    biodiversity and ecosystems.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section-4">
  <title>Section 4</title>
  <sec id="proposal-2-monocropping-affects-on-soil">
    <title>Proposal 2: Monocropping Affects on Soil</title>
    <p>Justification: Monocropping is a common agricultural practice
    where a single crop is grown for an amount of time. This agriculture
    practice is shown to cause diminishing effects on soil health, which
    accoring to
    (<xref alt="Belete &amp; Yadete, 2023" rid="ref-belete2023effect" ref-type="bibr">Belete
    &amp; Yadete, 2023</xref>) can have serious economic consequences.
    Monocropping increases soil infertility which decreases crop yields
    and soil quality.
    (<xref alt="Belete &amp; Yadete, 2023" rid="ref-belete2023effect" ref-type="bibr">Belete
    &amp; Yadete, 2023</xref>) also illustrates that monocropping causes
    changes in “soil microbial communities, nutrient availability, and
    allelopathy effect”. Additionally, often times as farmers try to
    combate decreasing yields by using synthetic fertilizers, which is
    very bad for soil health. Ultimately, monocropping is not
    sustainable for either the environment or the economy, thus a change
    is needed. Further studies are also needed to quantify monocroppings
    effect in order to spur change.
    (<xref alt="Katherasala et al., 2024" rid="ref-katherasala2024unveiling" ref-type="bibr">Katherasala
    et al., 2024</xref>) empashise the importance of educating farmers
    of monocultures harmful effect and alternative sustainable farming
    methods. Furthermore, with a reduce in crop fields, food security
    for many communities will be put at risk. Thus, clearly understand
    monocroppings affects on soil health and fertily is important for
    safeguarding food security.</p>
    <p>Research objective/question/hypothesis: This study will aim to
    analyze the long-term effects of mono-cropping on soil health. For
    the sake of this study, soil health will be measure by soil
    fertility, soil diversity, and nutrient cycling. The hypothesis for
    this study is: Over time mono-cropping depletes soil health,
    fertility, and biodiversity.</p>
    <p>Proposed Methods: The datasets used will include variables such
    as: soil pH, organic matter content, microbial diversity, and
    nutrient levels. Data on crop yield would also be a helpful
    comparisson. I will get my data maily from the USDA’s National
    Resources Inventory. I think both ANOVA tests or regression analysis
    would work for testing my hypothesis. I intend to use data from the
    U.S. and that was collected over a span of 10 years.</p>
    <p>Expected Outcomes: I expect to see that moncropping leads to a
    decline in soil health over time. Which will emphasize the
    importance for farmer to switch to more sustainable farming
    practices.</p>
  </sec>
</sec>
</body>

<back>
<ref-list>
  <title></title>
  <ref id="ref-pleasants2013milkweed">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Pleasants</surname><given-names>John M</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Oberhauser</surname><given-names>Karen S</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Milkweed loss in agricultural fields because of herbicide use: Effect on the monarch butterfly population</article-title>
      <source>Insect Conservation and Diversity</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley Online Library</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
      <volume>6</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>135</fpage>
      <lpage>144</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-zaya2017long">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Zaya</surname><given-names>David N</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Pearse</surname><given-names>Ian S</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Spyreas</surname><given-names>Greg</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Long-term trends in midwestern milkweed abundances and their relevance to monarch butterfly declines</article-title>
      <source>BioScience</source>
      <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
      <volume>67</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>343</fpage>
      <lpage>356</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-kumar2006spatial">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Sunil</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Stohlgren</surname><given-names>Thomas J</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>Geneva W</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Spatial heterogeneity influences native and nonnative plant species richness</article-title>
      <source>Ecology</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley Online Library</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
      <volume>87</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <fpage>3186</fpage>
      <lpage>3199</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-byrne2010impacts">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>Kerry M</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Lauenroth</surname><given-names>William K</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>Lindsay</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Impacts of nonnative plant species on production and diversity in the front range of colorado</article-title>
      <source>Western North American Naturalist</source>
      <publisher-name>BioOne</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
      <volume>70</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>288</fpage>
      <lpage>295</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-kolevcek2020shifts">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Koleček</surname><given-names>Jaroslav</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Adamı́k</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Reif</surname><given-names>Jiřı́</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Shifts in migration phenology under climate change: Temperature vs. Abundance effects in birds</article-title>
      <source>Climatic Change</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
      <volume>159</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>177</fpage>
      <lpage>194</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-tomotani2018climate">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Tomotani</surname><given-names>Barbara M</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Jeugd</surname><given-names>Henk van der</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Gienapp</surname><given-names>Phillip</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Hera</surname><given-names>Iván de la</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Pilzecker</surname><given-names>Jos</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Teichmann</surname><given-names>Corry</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>Marcel E</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Climate change leads to differential shifts in the timing of annual cycle stages in a migratory bird</article-title>
      <source>Global change biology</source>
      <publisher-name>Wiley Online Library</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year>
      <volume>24</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>823</fpage>
      <lpage>835</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-belete2023effect">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Belete</surname><given-names>Tegegn</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Yadete</surname><given-names>Eshetu</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Effect of mono cropping on soil health and fertility management for sustainable agriculture practices: A review</article-title>
      <source>Plant Sci</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <fpage>192</fpage>
      <lpage>197</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-katherasala2024unveiling">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Katherasala</surname><given-names>Srinivas</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bheenaveni</surname><given-names>Ram Shepherd</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Chinthakindi</surname><given-names>Parandamulu</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Vadlakonda</surname><given-names>Divya</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Kummari</surname><given-names>Nithyanandam</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Bandi</surname><given-names>Sushmita Susan</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Unveiling the detrimental impacts of intensive chemical use and monoculture on soil health and sustainable development goal 15: Life on land in telangana</article-title>
      <source>Journal of Lifestyle and SDGs Review</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2024">2024</year>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>10</fpage>
      <lpage>47172</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
</ref-list>
</back>



</article>